A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests, Series G FA316
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests, Series G
1896-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Standard Oil Company
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Rockefeller, Winthrop
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Spelman Fund
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Rockefeller, John D.
Spelman family
Rockefeller family
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, David
Davison Fund
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Sealantic Fund, New York
International Education Board
Rockefeller University
FA316
136 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
The files found in this series include correspondence by members of the Rockefeller family and their representatives and the officials of various institutions. Most of the material is unsolicited requests for aid. The material on institutions in which the family took an active interest, such as the International Houses, includes analysis, reports, general correspondence, contributions, and administration.
The Schools section and the Colleges section both include information on the schools attended by the Rockefeller brothers and cousins. There is a significant amount of information about the University of Chicago. The Foreign Colleges section includes a substantial amount of information on the University of Paris.
The family member who appears most prominently in this series is John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Other family members are John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and Winthrop Rockefeller.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
World War I; World War II; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Travel; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); United States; Urban policy; Urban renewal; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Folk art; Religion; Public welfare; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Economics; Economic policy; Economic development; Art; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Education -- United States; Education; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Business; Arts; International economic relations; International cooperation; International relations; International education; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Medical education; Medical research; Maternal health services; Medical care; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Philanthropy -- United States; Performing arts; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Public policy; Philanthropy; Public health administration; Public health; Prohibition; Standard Oil Company; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Rockefeller, Winthrop; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller Center; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Spelman Fund; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Rockefeller, John D.; Spelman family; Rockefeller family; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, David; Davison Fund; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Sealantic Fund, New York; International Education Board; Rockefeller University
- Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences
  - Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, 1905-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    John D. Rockefeller contributes to concert building in Brooklyn; declines to endow Academy. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes $250,000 to Brooklyn Botanical Gardens. David Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd life members. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    File Plan note
    145
  - Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
- Carnegie Boards
  - Carnegie Boards, 1902-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    By-Laws and early history of Carnegie organizations. Exchange of information on possible projects. African missionaries. Dinners, meetings, reports on programs. Correspondents include E. P. Keppel, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    161
  - Carnegie Boards, 1930-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carnegie Boards, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By-Laws and early history of Carnegie organizations. Exchange of information on possible projects. African missionaries. Dinners, meetings, reports on programs. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. guaranteed endowment note to Chase National Bank to buy land near United Nations, 1949. Correspondents include E. P. Keppel, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Carnegie Boards, 1947, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
  - Carnegie Boards, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carnegie Boards - David Rockefeller Interests, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    David Rockefeller elected to board of trustees of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace in 1947. Treasurer in 1949. Hiss resignation, search for new President. Programs; history of fund. Congressional investigations. Proposed programs, David Rockefeller comments and suggestions. 1961 gift to scholarship fund. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Alger Hiss, John Foster Dulles, James T. Shotwell.
    161D
  - Carnegie Boards - David Rockefeller Interests, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carnegie Boards - David Rockefeller Interests, 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Carnegie Boards - Carnegie Institution of Washington, D. C., 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    David Rockefeller a trustee in 1952; selection of new trustees; report on research. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
    161D1
  - Carnegie Boards - Carnegie Institution of Washington, D. C., 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 0009A)
  - Carnegie Boards - Carnegie Institution of Washington, D. C. - Invitations, 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 0009B)
    Invitations to John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller to attend special meetings; declined.
  - Carnegie Boards - Carnegie Institution of Washington, D. C. - Invitations, 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 0009C)
  - Carnegie Boards - Purchase of Land - New Building, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    David Rockefeller suggests new building for Carnegie Endowment near United Nations, contributes $60,000 toward furnishings. Purchase of land, construction; rental of space to non-profit organizations and a restaurant. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, W. T. Lindquist, J. E. Johnson.
  - Carnegie Boards - Winslow's World Affairs Project, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Attempt to raise international educational level of Americans. David Rockefeller supported project in beginning; project never completed. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Richard S. Winslow, W. T. Lindquist.
  - Carnegie Boards - Winslow's World Affairs Project, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Carnegie Boards - Winslow's World Affairs Project, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carnegie Boards - David Rockefeller Interests, 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Carnegie Boards - David Rockefeller - Contributions, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 0014A)
    For building expansion, special projects, Bilderberg Conference.
- Chinese Mass Education Movement
  - Chinese Mass Education Movement, 1927-1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Using simplified Chinese alphabet, James Yen tried to broaden education in China. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution, 1930. Discussion of value of movement; support by Rockefeller Foundation. Wartime fund raising efforts by Yen; deteriorating conditions in China. Efforts to extend Yen's techniques into Latin America.
    196
  - Chinese Mass Education Movement, 1933-1945 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chinese Mass Education Movement - Contributions, 1948-1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    By Nelson A. Rockefeller and Laurance S. Rockefeller to aid visual educational programs.
  - Chinese Mass Education Movement - Contributions, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 0017A)
- Educational Organizations
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Association's work; Winthrop Rockefeller's discussion with Thomas Dewey on use of tax monies in supporting schools. Contributions by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Winthrop Rockefeller becomes member of Board. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Thomas Dewey.
    114
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 0018A)
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association, 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 0019A)
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association - Contributions, 1913-1951 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Contributions of about $4,000 a year to a group of citizens conducting special studies and programs to improve education. Contributions to current expenses and to cost of distributing Hanus School report. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association - May 7, 1932 Pledge, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution used to support a "progressive" New York grade school. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - Educational Organizations - Public Education Association - Public School #61 Project - Pledge, February 27, 1928, 1927-1931 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Experimental classes conducted by Public Education Association; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s committee finances part of school budget for five years. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, O. W. Caldwell.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1932-1949 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Various educational programs, controversies, committees; no Rockefeller involvement in most cases. Nelson A. Rockefeller contributions to Eisenhower fellowship, 1954-1958; David Rockefeller contributions to Atlantic Foundation for Education of the Free. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Gene Setzer, R. C. Bates, Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    114.1
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 0023A)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 0024A)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 0025A)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 26A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - Committee for Refugee Education, Inc., 1940-1947 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Description of work; no Rockefeller interest.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - Committee for Refugee Education, Inc., 1947 (Box 4, Folder 0027A)
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - Open Road, 1939-1951 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Educational travel; no Rockefeller interest.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - Progressive Education Association, 1939-1947 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    The organization changed its name to the American Education Fellowship. Appeal to Nelson A. Rockefeller declined.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - World Education Service Council, Inc., 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Friendship plan. No Rockefeller interest.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - Fund for Advancement of Education, 1952-1960 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Information on Fund. No action.
    General note
    Open per CLS, May 25, 2005.
  - Educational Organizations - Miscellaneous - United States National Student Association, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    David Rockefeller makes two small gifts to convention travel expenses.
  - Educational Organizations - Integration - Congress of Racial Equality, 1947-1961 (Box 5, Folder 0032A)
    Information on various integration organizations. No Rockefeller interest expressed in this file.
    114.1A
  - Educational Organizations - Integration - Congress of Racial Equality, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 0032B)
  - Educational Organizations - American Council on Education, 1940-1956 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Arthur W. Packard a member; David Rockefeller contribution through Council for support of American school in Ecuador. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller.
    114.2
  - Educational Organizations - American Council on Education, 1940-1956 (Box 5, Folder 0033A)
  - Educational Organizations - American Council on Education - Hawkes Committee, 1925-1933 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution for study of vocational guidance in higher education. Vocational testing service supported by General Education Board grew from this. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift of $60,000. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Educational Organizations - Youthbuilders, Inc., 1941-1949 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Organized to education public school children (8-16) in responsible citizenship. David Rockefeller contributed for several years. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, David Rockefeller.
    114.3
  - Educational Organizations - World Association for Adult Education, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. non-recurring contribution toward maintaining house for world center for adult education. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson.
  - Educational Organizations - New York Adult Educational Council, 1929-1954 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Education for immigrants. Supported by Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial until 1929; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. refused to continue support. John D. Rockefeller 3rd contribution in 1949. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel.
    114.4
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Service for Juniors, 1921-1943 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Provided scholarships and job counseling for high school students. Expanded in 1945 to provide counseling for veterans. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts through advisory committee, 1922-1934. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Sandra Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    114.5
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Service for Juniors, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 0038A)
    Provided scholarships and job counseling for high school students. Expanded in 1945 to provide counseling for veterans. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Sandra Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Advisory Service, 1944-1961 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Advisory Service, 1954-1961 (Box 5, Folder 39A)
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Research Bureau, 1932-1951 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    Organization interested in developing character and responsibility, and in getting scholarships to better schools for talented boys. No Rockefeller contributions, although the brothers were interested for awhile. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles K. Taylor.
    114.6
  - Educational Organizations - Vocational Research Bureau, 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 0040A)
  - Educational Organizations - National Advisory Committee on Illiteracy, 1927-1933 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. makes several small contributions to committee working to eliminate illiteracy in America. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, Ray Wilbur.
    114.7
  - Educational Organizations - National Fund for Medical Education, 1949-1960 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    Fund-raising; no family contributions; Laurance S. Rockefeller purchased tables at special dinners. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, David Rockefeller.
  - Educational Organizations - National Fund for Medical Education, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 0042A)
  - Educational Organizations - National Education Association, 1908-1961 (Box 6, Folder 43)